Guide to the Radio Entertainers and Announcers Collection 1937-1945 (Bulk 1942-1943) PR 95
New-York Historical Society
Radio entertainers and announcers collection
1937-1945 (Bulk 1942-1943)
New-York Historical Society
PR 95
2.52 Linear feet (Approximately 1,500 photographs)
Photographs depicting popular radio performers during World War II, often engaged in war conservation efforts.
Provenance
Gift of Thomas Calvin Linn, New York Times reporter, Dec. 16 1942 and Sep. 15 1943
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Content Note
This collection features roughly 1, 500 publicity photographs of wartime radio personalities, including Fred Allen, Jack Benny, Edgar Bergen, and Abbott and Costello. The entertainers are often pictured promoting war conservation and recycling, or broadcasting from bases around the world. ABC, CBS, NBC, WOR-Mutual, and WEVD are among the networks represented. NBC "Helpmate" actors are pictured purchasing war bonds above their regular quotas; in the drive to sell war bonds, the actors bought bonds each time the Allies bombed Berlin. There is also a series of photographs showing radio employees picking up short wave communications at the "listening post," which were then transmitted to the News Room. Overall, this collection documents the impact not only of radio on troop morale but also of the war itself on home front entertainment.
Arrangement
The photographs are organized alphabetically by entertainer, and then by subject. Entertainers with 3 or more photographs were assigned their own folder. A complete list of entertainers is available in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Other World War II-era material in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections includes WWII Recruiting and Civilian Defense Posters in the Poster File (PR 055), prints in the Subject File (PR 068), and photographs in the John Albok Photograph Collection (PR 001) and World War II Photograph Collection (PR 076).
Portraits.; Actors.; Radio announcing.; Singers.; Entertainers.; Musicians.; Gelatin silver prints.; Conductors (Music).; Comedians -- United States -- Portraits; Radio actors and actresses; Radio broadcasting -- United States.; Radio in propaganda -- United States.; Singers -- United States -- Portraits; World War, 1939-1945 -- Mass media and the war; Photographs.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work.; Barton, Vera (Singer); Benny, Jack, 1894-1974; Bergen, Edgar, 1903-1978; Borge, Victor; Brice, Fanny; Burns, George, 1896-1996; Cantor, Eddie, 1892-1964; Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc.; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Costello, Lou; Crosby, Bing, 1903-1977; Dragonette, Jessica; Durante, Jimmy; Erickson, Louise; Fitzgerald, Ella; Francis, Arlene; Gardner, Ed, 1901-1961; Godfrey, Arthur, 1903-1983; Goodman, Benny, 1909-1986; Haenschen, W. Gus. (Walter Gustave), 1889-1980; Hayes, Helen, 1900-1993; Hersholt, Jean, 1886-1956; Hope, Bob, 1903-2003; Ives, Burl, 1909-1995; Jessel, George, 1898-1981; Jolson, Al, 1886-1950; Kyser, Kay; Lawrence, Marjorie, 1908-; Loy, Myrna, 1905-1993; McCambridge, Mercedes; National Broadcasting Company. Radio-Recording Division; Oliver, Edna May, 1883-1942; Pons, Lily, 1898-1976; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Shore, Dinah, 1917-1994; Skelton, Red, 1913-1997; Smith, Kate, 1907-1986; Stewart, James, 1908-1997; Stone, Ezra, 1917-1994; Waring, Fred, 1900-1984; Welles, Orson, 1915-1985; WEVD (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); WOR (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); Zyne, Murray; Allen, Fred, 1894-1956; Allen, Gracie, 1902-1964; Ameche, Don; American Broadcasting Company; Aot, Bud
- Entertainers and Announcers, Alphabetical List
  - Adams, Franklin - Astaire, Fred, 1942 Apr. 1-1943 Mar. 16 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbott, Bud and Costello, Lou, 1942 Sep. 23-1942 Dec. 18 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ace Goodman and Jane, 1948 Oct. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Allen, Arthur, and Fennelly, Parker, 1942 Dec. 15-1943 Mar. 16 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Allen, Fred, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Allen, Mel, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ameche, Don, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baker, Jack - Boland, Mary, 1942 Jun. 26-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bonura, Zeke - Byrne, Barry, 1941-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barber, Red, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Barlow, Ernesta, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Barton, Vera, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bauer, Charita, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Beck, Jackson, 1942-1943 Jan. 19 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bellauer, Harry, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Benny, Jack, 1942 Mar. 11-1943 Jan. 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bergen, Edgar, 1942 Jan. 14-1943 Mar. 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bernie, Ben, 1941 Sep. 9-1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Black, Frank, 1942-1943 Mar. 2 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Borge, Victor, 1942 Aug. 8-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Breneman, Tom, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brice, Fanny, 1940 Nov. 1-1942 Nov. 10 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Burns, Bob, 1942 Oct.-1943 Mar. 23 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
  - Burns, George and Allen, Gracie, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
  - Byron, Ed, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cabanne, Mimi - Coelho, Olga, 1942 Jul. 31-1943 Mar. 3 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Colbert, Regina - Curtin, Joseph, 1942 Oct. 7-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cantor, Eddie, 1942-1943 Mar. 30 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Close, Upton, 1942 Mar. 3-1942 Nov. 3 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
  - Copland, Aaron, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correll, Charles and Gosden, Freeman, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31)
  - Courtney, Diane, 1942 Sep. 21-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
  - Crosby, Bing, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
  - Crosby, Bob, 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
  - Cugat, Xavier, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 35)
  - Damon, Les - Dinsdale, Shirley, 1941 Mar. 6-1943 Feb. 23 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 36)
  - Dodson, Jon - Dutton, Laura Deane, 1942 Mar. 3-1943 Mar. 16 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 37)
  - Day, Dennis, 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 38)
  - Dinning Sisters, The, 1942 Aug. 5-1943 Apr. 6 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 39)
  - Donald, Peter, 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 40)
  - Dragonette, Jessica, 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 41)
  - Dudley, Paul, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 42)
  - Eddy, Nelson - Everett, Harry, 1942 Jun. 26-1943 Mar. 23 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 43)
  - Edwards, Ralph, 1942 Sep. 8-1943 Jan. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 44)
  - Ellis, Dellie, 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 45)
  - Erickson, Louise, 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 46)
  - Evans, Dale, 1942 Sep. 25-1942 Dec. 21 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 47)
  - Farrell, Jimmy - Fuller, Barbara, 1942 Feb. 4-1943 Mar. 9 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 48)
  - Fennelly, Parker, 1942-1943 Feb. 16 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 49)
  - Francis, Arlene, 1942-1943 Feb. 23 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 50)
  - Fridell, Vivian, 1942 Jul. 9-1943 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 51)
  - Garbell, Rosemary-Gwenn, Edmund, 1942 Jun.-1943 Apr. 13 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 52)
  - Gardner, Ed, 1942 Mar.-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 53)
  - Gerson, Betty Lou, 1942 Jul. 21-1943 Apr. 6 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 54)
  - Godfrey, Arthur, 1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 55)
  - Godwin, Earl, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 56)
  - Goodman, Al, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 57)
  - Goodman, Benny, 1942 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 58)
  - Grey, Nan, 1942-1943 Jan. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 59)
  - Hackett, Bobby-Henry, Bill, 1942 Mar. 12-1943 Sep. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 60)
  - Hern, Art-Husing, Ted, 1941 May 19-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 61)
  - Haenschen, Gus, 1942 Jan. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 62)
  - Hawk, Bob, 1941 Dec. 31-1942 Jul. 1 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 63)
  - Hayes, Helen, 1942 Jul.-1943 Sep. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 64)
  - Hershfield, Harry, 1942 Oct. 7-1943 Feb. 2 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 65)
  - Hersholt, Jean, 1942 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 66)
  - Higby, Mary Jane, 1942 Dec. 15-1943 Mar. 22 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 67)
  - Hill, Patricia, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 68)
  - Hookey, Bobby, 1942-1943 Feb. 9 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 69)
  - Hope, Bob, 1942 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 70)
  - Houston, Josephine, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 71)
  - Hulick, Budd, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 72)
  - Ives, Burl, 1942 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 73)
  - Jagger, Dean-Jordan, Joyce, 1942 Jul. 21-1943 Mar. 22 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 74)
  - James, Harry, 1942 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 75)
  - Jessell, George, 1942 Jan. (Offsite-box 3, Folder 76)
  - Jolson, Al, 1942 Oct.-1943 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 77)
  - Jordan, Jim and Marian, 1942 Feb. 2-1943 Feb. 23 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 78)
  - Kallen, Kitty-Kilty, Jack, 1942 Apr. 6-1943 Mar. 22 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 79)
  - King, Pete-Kupfer, Kurt, 1942 Aug.-1943 May (Offsite-box 4, Folder 80)
  - Kaye, Sammy, 1942 Sep. 25-1943, Jan. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 81)
  - Kelk, Jackie, 1942 Apr. 25-1942 Aug. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 82)
  - Kilpack, Bennett, 1942 Oct. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 83)
  - Klowden, Nina, 1942 Dec. 28-1943 Feb. 16 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 84)
  - Kummer, Eloise, 1942 Sep. 14-1943 Jan. 4 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 85)
  - Kupperman, Joel, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 86)
  - Kyser, Kay, 1942 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 87)
  - Lake, Arthur-Leinsdorf, Erich, 1941 May 15-1943 Apr. 20 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 88)
  - Leonard, Lillian-Lyon, Priscilla, 1942 Jan. 7-1943 Aug. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 89)
  - Lawrence, Marjorie, 1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 90)
  - Leibert, Dick, 1942 Apr. 1-1942 Dec. 21 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 91)
  - Lester, Jerry, 1942 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 92)
  - MacCormack, Franklyn-Menser, C.L., 1942 Feb. 25-1943 Mar. 31 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 93)
  - Michael, Mary-Music Maids and Phil, The, 1941 Jun. 9-1943 Mar. 2 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 94)
  - McCambridge, Mercedes, 1942 Sep. 16-1943 Mar. 2 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 95)
  - McClain, Jimmy, 1942 Sep. 8-1943 Jan. 19 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 96)
  - McEvoy, J.P., 1942 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 97)
  - McLaughlin, Don, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 98)
  - Melton, James, 1942 Mar.-1943 Apr. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 99)
  - Mercer, Mary Ann, 1942 Feb. 25-1942 Dec. 8 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 100)
  - Merrick, Margaret, 1942-1943 Jan. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 101)
  - Millay, Edna St, Vincent, 1942 Sep. 30-1948 Dec. 28 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 102)
  - Moore, Garry, 1942 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 103)
  - Moore, Grace, 1942 Jul. 1-1943 Sep. (Offsite-box 4, Folder 104)
  - Morgan, Frank, 1942 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 105)
  - Moylan Sisters, The, 1942 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 106)
  - Nash, Clarence-Novak, Frank J., 1942 Mar. 30-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 107)
  - Neil, Marcia, 1942 Oct. 14-1943 Apr. 20 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 108)
  - Neumayer, Marilou, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 109)
  - Obeler, Arch-Owens, Ruth, 1942 Oct. 7-1943 Feb. 16 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 110)
  - O'Keefe, Walter, 1942 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 111)
  - Oliver, Edna May, 1942 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 112)
  - Parker, Frank-Providnia, Zina, 1942 Mar. 10-1943 Mar. 16 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 113)
  - Paige, Raymond, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 114)
  - Palmer, Eileen, 1942 Jul. 29-1943 Feb. 2 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 115)
  - Patton, Mary, 1942 Aug. 25-1943 Mar. 9 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 116)
  - Peabody, Eddie, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 117)
  - Peaker, Ada Beth, 1942 Mar. 3-1943 Mar. 23 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 118)
  - Peary, Harold, 1941 Aug. 31-1943 Jan. 26 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 119)
  - Persons, Fern, 1942 Oct. 27-1943 Mar. 30 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 120)
  - Pons, Lily, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 121)
  - Porter, Roy, 1942 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 122)
  - Putnam, George F., 1942-1943 Mar. 30 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 123)
  - Raffetto, Michael-Robb, Stuart, 1942 Jun. 22-1943 Apr. 20 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 124)
  - Robinson, Edward G.-Ryder, Alfred, 1942 Jan.-1943 Mar. 16 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 125)
  - Riggs, Tommy, 1942-1943 Mar. 23 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 126)
  - Robinson, Bartlett, 1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 127)
  - Ross, Lanny, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 128)
  - Ryan, Patricia, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 129)
  - Sacco, Charles-Smith, Viola, 1942 Feb. 25-1943 Apr. 13 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 130)
  - Smolen, Vivian-Steele Sisters, The, 1942 Mar. 10-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 131)
  - Stevens, Julie-Swinney, Josephine, 1941-1943 Apr. 6 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 132)
  - Seymour, Anne, 1942 Jul. 29-1943 Jan. 19 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 133)
  - Shaw, Hollace, 1942-1943 Mar. 18 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 134)
  - Shayon, Robert Louis, 1942 Jul. (Offsite-box 5, Folder 135)
  - Sherman, Ransom, 1942 Jan. 9-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 136)
  - Shore, Dinah, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 137)
  - Simms, Ginny, 1942 Sep. 8-1943 Apr. 6 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 138)
  - Singleton, Penny, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 139)
  - Skelton, Red, 1942 Oct. 14-1943 Jan. 4 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 140)
  - Smith, Kate, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 141)
  - Stern, Bill, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 142)
  - Stewart, Jimmy, 1942 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 143)
  - Stone, Ezra, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 144)
  - Stoopnagle, Colonel, 1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 145)
  - Swarthout, Gladys, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 146)
  - Tamiroff, Akim-Tuttle, Lurene, 1942 Feb. 25-1943 Mar. 23 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 147)
  - Templeton, Alec, 1937 Jun. 19-1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 148)
  - Terry, Renee, 1943 Apr. (Offsite-box 6, Folder 149)
  - Thomas, John Charles, 1942 Aug.-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 150)
  - Thompson, Bill, 1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 151)
  - Uncle Arnold-Unger, Stella, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 152)
  - Valdes, Miguelito-Voorhees, Donald, 1942 Feb. 2-1943 Apr. 6 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 153)
  - Walpole, Helen-Worth, Betty, 1942 Feb.-1943 Mar. 16 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 154)
  - Waring, Fred, 1942-1943 Apr. 20 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 155)
  - Welles, Orson, 1941 Sep. 5-1942 Sep. (Offsite-box 6, Folder 156)
  - Widmark, Dick, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 157)
  - Williams, Florence, 1942 Sep. 23-1943 Feb. 16 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 158)
  - Willson, Meredith, 1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 159)
  - Winkler, Betty, 1942 Feb. 25-1943 Jan. 26 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 160)
  - Wismer, Harry, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 161)
  - Wood, Helen, 1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 162)
  - Woods, Lesley, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 163)
  - Yates, Dorothy-Young, Russ, 1942 Mar. 11-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 164)
  - Zyne, Murray, 1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 165)
- Subject List
  - Broadcasting Equipment and Technology, 1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 166)
  - CBS Listening Post, 1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 167)
  - Goodwin's Gym, 1942 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 168)
  - Shows, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 169)
  - Miscellaneous (captions, press releases), 1943 Feb. 10, undated (Offsite-box 6, Folder 170)
  - Unidentified, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 171)